A Guide to the Papers of the Gilmer Family 1856-1865
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Gilmer Family 1856-1865
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5194
This collection consists of 148 items on microfilm.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited in the University of Virginia Library for historical reference and photographing by Mr. M. C. Gilmer, Big Cedar Creek Farm, Lebanon, Virginia, on October 24, 1955.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of the Gilmer family is largely a collection of incoming correspondence received and retained by Cummings Gilmer of Lebanon, Russell County, Virginia, and his daughter, Martha. On examination of the correspondence, it appears that Cummings Gilmer and his wife, Mary, had the following children: Charles Hayes Gilmer, William Rives Gilmer, John Edmonson Gilmer, Martha J. Gilmer, and Sarah W. Gilmer. Cummings' brother, William Gilmer, and his wife, Jane, had a son, James A. Gilmer, who is also represented in the collection.
Of primary interest are the early letters of John E. Gilmer, describing life and events at Emory and Henry College (one of his essays describes a duel) and his letters as a Confederate soldier, some of which were apparently written in collaboration with his brother, William, whose Civil War letters constitute the largest portion of the collection. The news of war and family are also reflected in the letters of Charles H. Gilmer. Death or imprisonment befell James and his cousins towards the end of the war. Unfortunately, only a few items of outgoing correspondence (from Cummings, his daughter, Martha, and his brother, William) are extant in this collection.
Contents List
- John E. Gilmer, Essays and Compositions
  - "Downfall of Error" 1857 Mar, 1 p.
  - "The Glory and Shame of Americans" 1857 Apr 7, 2 p.
  - "The Glory..." (continued) 1857 Apr 29, 3 p.
  - "The Unicorn" 1857 Sep 8, 1 p.
  - "A Duel" 1858 Feb 27, 3 p.
  - ["A Duel"] n.d., 2 p.
  - [A duel at Emory on April 10th] n.d., 2 p.
  - "Order - Necessary to Prosperity" 1858 Mar 17, 3 p.
  - "Order & etc." n.d., 1 p.
  - "Young Men Should Seek Homes in the West" 1858 Apr 8, 1 p.
  - "Arnold" 1858 Apr 30, 2 p.
  - "The Mariners Compass" n.d., 1 p.
  - "Fortune Not to be Trusted" n.d., 2 p.
  - "The Pleasures of Memory" n.d., 1 p.
- John E. Gilmer, Letters to His Family
  - "Dear Pa & Ma" 1856 Aug 29, 3 p.
  - "Dear Pa & Ma" 1856 Oct 4, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1856 Dec 7, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1857 Jan 8, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1857 May 10, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa & Ma" 1857 Oct 4, 6 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1857 Dec 6, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1858 Jan 3, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1858 Feb 7, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa & Ma" 1858 Feb 7, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1858 Mar 7, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1858 Mar 21, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1858 Apr 4, 4 p.
  - "Dear Parents" 1858 Apr 8, 4 p.
  - "Beloved Sister" 1858 Apr 17, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1858 Apr 28, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1858 May 9, 4 p.
  - "Dear Rives" 1858 Jun 1, 2 p.
  - "A Few Items" n.d., 4 p.
  - "To All At Home" n.d., 2 p.
- John E. Gilmer, Letters to His Family
  (some letters are also signed by William R. Gilmer)
  - "Dear Parents" 1861 Jun 6, 4 p.
  - "Dear Parents" 1861 Jun 10, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa & Ma" 1861 Jun 19, 9 p.
  - "Dear Sisters & All" 1861 Jun 24, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa & Ma" 1861 Jul 1, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1861 Jul 8, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1861 Jul 21, 8 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1861 Jul 26, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa & Ma" 1861 Jul 31, 4 p.
  - "Dear Martha" 1861 Jul 31, 4 p.
  - fragments n.d., 4 p.
- William Gilmer to his Sons and Nephews
  - to James A. Gilmer 1862 Sep 10, 2 p.
  - to J.E. Gilmer 1862 Jul 17, 2 p.
- Cummings Gilmer Letters to His Sons
  (The letters are also signed by Mary Gilmer)
  - to J.E. and W.R. Gilmer 1861 Jun 22, 3 p.
  - "Deare Sons" 1861 Jul 26, 2 p.
  - to J.E. Gilmer 1861 Aug 21, 1 p.
- Charles H. Gilmer, Letters to His Family
  - "Dear Pa" 1862 May 14, 1 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1862 Jun 9, 2 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1862 Jun 15, 2 p.
  - "Dear Parents" 1862 Jul [1], 2 p.
  - "Dear Pa" [1862] Sep 2, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1862 Nov 26, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1862 Dec 16, 4 p.
  - "Dear Parents Brother & Sister" 1862 Dec 27, 3 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Jan 20, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Feb 10, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Feb 26, 4 p.
  - to his sister 1863 Mar 21, 2 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1863 Mar 30, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Apr 22, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 May 10, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 May 15, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 May 15, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 May 23, 4 p.
  - "Dear Uncle" 1863 May 26, 4 p.
  - "Dear Parents" 1863 Jun 21, 3 p.
  - "Dear Ma" 1863 Jun 28, 2 p.
  - "Dear Uncle" 1863 Jul 25, 2 p.
  - "Dear Parents" 1863 Jul 26, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Sep 14, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Oct 3, 4 p.
  - "Dear Parents" 1863 Oct 18, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1864 Feb 24, 2 p.
- William R. Gilmer, Letters to His Family
  - "Dear brothers" 1861 Jun 9, 2 p.
  - "Dear brothers" 1861 Jul 13, 6 p.
  - "Dear parents brothers & sisters" 1861 Aug 4, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1861 Aug 13, 2 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1861 Aug 15, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1861 Sep 9, 3 p.
  - "Dear parents brothers & Sisters" 1861 Sep 14, 3 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1861 Oct 5, 3 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1861 Oct 13, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1861 Oct 20, 2 p.
  - "Dear brother & Sister" 1861 Oct 22, 2 p.
  - "Dear brother & Sister" 1861 Nov 7, 3 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1861 Nov 7, 3 p.
  - "Dear Pa ma & Sister" 1861 Dec 9, 3 p.
  - "Dear Ma" 1861 Dec 22, 2 p.
  - fragment n.d., 1 p.
- William R. Gilmer, Letters to His Family
  - "Dear brother & Sisters" 1862 Jan 21, 3 p.
  - "Ma" 1862 Feb 7, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1862 Feb 10, 2 p.
  - "Dear Pa & ma" 1862 Feb 17, 2 p.
  - "Dear parents" 1862 Mar 26, 2 p.
  - "Dear friend" 1862 Apr 6, 2 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1862 Apr 15, 2 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1862 May 26, 3 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1862 Jun 14, 4 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1862 Jul 7, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sisters" 1862 Aug 13, 3 p.
  - "Dear Pa" 1862 Sep 7, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1862 Sep 28, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sisters" 1862 Oct 7, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1862 Nov 2, 2 p.
  - "Dear brother & Sister" [1862], 2 p.
- William R. Gilmer, Letters to His Family
  - "Dear Pa & Ma" 1863 May 16, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Jun 9, 3 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Jun 16, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Jun 19, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Jul 16, 4 p.
  - "Dear parents brother & Sisters" 1863 Jul 26, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sisters" 1863 Aug 15, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Aug 28, 4 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1863 Oct 5, 2 p.
  - "Dear Parents brothers & Sisters" 1863 Dec 4, 3 p.
  - "Dear Pa & Ma" 1863 Dec [17], 3 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1864 Mar 13, 3 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1864 Mar 19, 3 p.
  - "Dear Pa & Ma" 1864 Apr 8, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1864 Apr 17, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1864 Sep 3, 1 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1864 Sep 29, 2 p.
  - "Dear Sister" 1864 Nov 7, 1 p.
- James A. Gilmer, Letters
  - "Dear Uncle" 1861 Sep 10, 2 p.
  - "Dear Friend" 1863 Jan 28, 3 p.
- Martha J. Gilmer, Letters to Her Brothers
  - "Dear Brothers" 1861 Jun 14, 4 p.
  - "Dear Brothers" 1861 Jul 26, 4 p.
  - "Dear Brothers" 1864 Aug 25, 2 p.
  - "Dear Brothers" 1864 Oct 25, 2 p.
  - "Dear Brothers" 1865 Jan 15, 4 p.
  - "Dear Brothers" n.d., 2 p.
- Miscellaneous Gilmer Family Correspondence
  - [?] to John E. Gilmer 1857 Mar 4, 4 p.
  - "your Doctor" to J.E. Gilmer 1861 Jul 31, 2 p.
  - George R. Cowan to "Dear Uncle" [1861] Aug 17, 2 p.
  - [?] to "Dear brother" 1861 Aug 20, 2 p.
  - Robert E. Cowan to "Dear Uncle" 1861 Aug 20, 1 p.
  - Edward D. Gray to John E. Gilmer 1861 Aug 30, 2 p.
  - George R. Cowan to "Dear Uncle" 1861 Oct 6, 3 p.
  - [?] to "Dear Sister" (fragment) 1863 Jul 16, 3 p.
  - Cummings Gilmer to "Der paw" 1863 Dec 9, 3 p.
  - S. Gilmer to "Dear brother" 1864 Aug, 2 p.
  - [?] to [?] 1864 Oct 18, 1 p.
  - [?] to [?] n.d., 2 p.